Finding Aid for the Carol Hamilton Scott and James M. Lawson, Jr. Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Carol Hamilton Scott and James M. Lawson, Jr. Collection
1950-1953
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0813
.21 Linear feet
Biography/History
Carol Hamilton Scott graduated from Ohio Wesleyan University in 1953. Since her graduation, her mission has been to provide services to eliminate poverty and illiteracy in the Springfield, Ohio, community.
During the 1960s she was active in the Civil Rights Movement and directed the Springfield Urban League’s Leadership Development Project. Through her participation in the National Council of Negro Women, she helped welfare mothers obtain college scholarships to continue their education and pursue professional careers.
Carol was the first woman elected to the Board of Directors of Wilberforce University and the first African-American woman to serve on the Board of Directors of Banc Ohio National Bank and later, National City Bank. She has held leadership positions with numerous community organizations and has been the recipient of a multitude of awards. In 1994, she was inducted into the Ohio Women’s Hall of Fame in recognition of her dedication and service to others.
Scope and Contents
This .21 linear foot collection contains 30 pieces of correspondence from James M. Lawson, Jr. to Carol Hamilton during his time in prison for refusing to enlist in the Korean War. It also includes two pieces of correspondence from the Department of Justice to Carol Hamilton receiving permission to write James Lawson, three essays, and three postcards.
- Correspondence — Incoming, 1951
  - - May - (3)
  - - June — (2)
  - - July — (1)
  - - August — (4)
  - - September - (3)
  - - October — (1)
  - - November — (3)
  - - December — (3) ©
- Correspondence — Incoming —, 1952
  - - January — (3)
  - - February — (3)
  - - March — (2)
  - - April — (1)
  - - May — (1)
- Correspondence — Incoming —, 1953
  - - Postcards (3)
- Correspondence — Incoming —, 1951
  - - Department of Justice - (2)
- Essays — (3 were attached together)
  - - ‘Alternative to Destruction’, by James Lawson, March 17, 1950
  - - ‘Gold on Old Mac’, by Paul F. Ross, March 17, 1950
  - - ‘Believe and Live’, by Clarence Higgins